huntonprivacyblog.com 2011-09-26

# Privacy policy : Privacy & Information Security Law Blog

###  [Use of Google Analytics Now Lawful in Germany, Subject to Certain Guidelines](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/09/articles/european-union-1/use-of-google-analytics-now-lawful-in-germany-subject-to-certain-guidelines/)

On September 15, 2011, the data protection authority of the German federal state of Hamburg (the “DPA”) published a [press release](http://www.datenschutz-hamburg.de/news/detail/article/beanstandungsfreier-betrieb-von-google-analytics-ab-sofort-moeglich.html) confirming that Google has significantly improved compliance with respect to the implementation of Google Analytics in Germany.  This finding is the result of two years of fruitful dialog between Google and the DPA, which was acting on behalf of the conference of German data protection authorities responsible for the private sector (the “Düsseldorfer Kreis”).

According to the DPA, Google has now improved the use of Google Analytics by:

  * Giving users of major browsers ( _i.e._ , Internet Explorer, Mozilla Firefox, Google Chrome, Safari and Opera) the opportunity to object to the collection of their data by using the [Google Analytics Opt-out Browser Add-on](http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de) function;
  * offering website operators the option to request anonymization of IP addresses that are collected (by deleting the last digits); and
  * entering into a data processing agreement with website operators regarding the processing of personal data in compliance with the German Federal Data Protection Act (“FDPA”).

The DPA endorsed Google’s intention to implement technical changes throughout Europe, and emphasized that “it is not Google, but the website operators using this product [as data controllers] that are responsible for ensuring privacy-friendly use.”

Against this background, the DPA also issued [guidelines](http://www.datenschutz-hamburg.de/uploads/media/GoogleAnalytics_Hinweise_Webseitenbetreiber_in_Hamburg.pdf) for helping website operators ensure compliance.  According to the DPA, website operators should:

  * Enter into a data processing agreement with Google regarding the processing of personal data, using a [standard agreement](http://www.google.de/intl/de/analytics/tos.pdf) approved by the DPAs that imposes specific obligations on data controllers ( _i.e._ , website operators) in accordance with the FDPA;
  * inform users about the use of Google Analytics in their privacy policy, and also provide users with an opportunity to object by using the following link: <http://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout?hl=de>;
  * entrust Google with the anonymization of IP addresses by appropriately adjusting the [Google Analytics Program Code](http://code.google.com/intl/de/apis/analytics/docs/gaJS/gaJSApi_gat.html#_gat._anonymizeIp) privacy settings, and using the “_anonymizelp()” function on their websites; and
  * delete all old data that was collected using non-compliant Google Analytics, close old Google Analytics Profiles and establish new profiles.

The DPA cautioned that additional improvements might be necessary in the future, particularly following the implementation of the [EU’s new cookies law](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/06/articles/european-union-1/hunton-hosts-webinar-on-preparing-for-the-eu-cookie-law/) and the introduction of Internet Protocol version 6 in Germany.

For further information on the DPA's press release, please contact [Dr. Jörg Hladjk](http://www.hunton.com/jorg_hladjk/) in the Brussels office of Hunton & Williams.

###  [Outsourcers Exempt from India's Privacy Regulations](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/08/articles/information-security/outsourcers-exempt-from-indias-privacy-regulations/)

Posted on August 24, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On August 24, 2011, the Government of India’s Ministry of Communications & Information Technology [issued a clarification](http://pib.nic.in/newsite/erelease.aspx?relid=74990) regarding India’s new privacy regulations, known as the Information Technology (Reasonable Security Practices and Procedures and Sensitive Personal Data or Information) Rules, 2011 (the “Rules”), under Section 43A of the Information Technology Act 2000.

Under the Rules, which [were first published on April 11](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/05/articles/international/india-drafts-new-privacy-regulations/), an individual’s prior written consent is required to process or disclose sensitive personal data.  Outsourcing service providers in India had been concerned that it would be impossible to comply with this requirement given that they typically do not have direct contact with the individuals from whom they would need to obtain consent.  The clarification states that any “body corporate providing services relating to collection, storage, dealing or handling of sensitive personal data or information under contractual obligation with any legal entity located within or outside India” is exempt from the requirement to obtain consent.  Accordingly, Indian outsourcing service providers will not need to obtain consent from individuals before processing their data, regardless of whether the outsourcing services are provided to companies based in India or abroad.  The Rules will apply only to Indian companies that obtain sensitive personal data directly.

The clarification also defines “provider of information” (a term used in the Rules), as “those natural persons who provide sensitive personal data or information to a body corporate.”

Since the [Rules were published](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/05/articles/international/india-drafts-new-privacy-regulations/), it has not been clear how they would apply in practice to companies that outsource their data processing activities to India.  The Indian government’s clarification should come as a welcome relief to the Indian outsourcing industry, and to the companies that use Indian outsourcing services.

View the [Ministry’s Press Note](http://pib.nic.in/newsite/erelease.aspx?relid=74990).

###  [Representative Mary Bono Mack Releases Discussion Draft of the SAFE Data Act](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/06/articles/enforcement-1/representative-mary-bono-mack-releases-discussion-draft-of-the-safe-data-act/)

Posted on June 17, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On June 13, 2011, Representative [Mary Bono Mack](http://bono.house.gov/) (R-CA) released a [discussion draft](http://bono.house.gov/UploadedFiles/Data_Breach_Draft.pdf) of the Secure and Fortify Data Act (the “SAFE Data Act”), which is designed to “protect consumers by requiring reasonable security policies and procedures to protect data containing personal information, and to provide for nationwide notice in the event of a security breach.”  Representative Bono Mack is Chairman of the House Subcommittee on Commerce, Manufacturing and Trade.  In a [press release](http://bono.house.gov/News/DocumentSingle.aspx?DocumentID=246029), Representative Bono Mack remarked that “E-commerce is a vital and growing part of our economy.  We should take steps to embrace and protect it – and that starts with robust cyber security.”  She added that “consumers have a right to know when their personal information has been compromised, and companies and other organizations have an overriding responsibility to promptly alert them.”

The legislation would apply to persons engaged in interstate commerce that own or possess data containing personal information related to that commercial activity, including information brokers and third parties contracted to maintain data on the person’s behalf.  Under the SAFE Data Act, the term “personal information” means an individual’s first name or initial and last name, address or phone number, in combination with any one or more of the following: (1) Social Security number, (2) driver’s license number, passport number, military ID or similar number, or (3) financial account number, or credit or debit card number, and any required security code, access code or password that is necessary to permit access to individual’s financial account.  The SAFE Data Act grants the FTC the authority to modify the definition of personal information to the extent necessary to effectuate the Act’s purposes. 

In brief, the bill features two key elements:

  * _Data Security Requirements.  _ The bill instructs the Federal Trade Commission to promulgate regulations that require persons to establish and implement information security policies and procedures regarding the treatment and protection of personal information.  The SAFE Data Act exempts from this requirement entities subject to the Gramm-Leach-Bliley Act and HIPAA, as well as certain service providers.
  * _Breach Notification Requirements._   In the event of a breach, which the SAFE Data Act defines as “any unauthorized access to or acquisition of data in electronic form containing personal information,” a person must: (1) notify law enforcement within 48 hours of discovery unless the breach involves the inadvertent access or acquisition of data by the person’s employee or agent and (2) assess the nature and scope of the breach and take mitigating steps to prevent further disclosure.  If the person determines, based on the assessment, that the breach presents a “reasonable risk of identity theft, fraud, or other unlawful conduct,” within 48 hours the person must notify the FTC and begin to notify affected individuals “as promptly as possible.”  Similar to various state breach laws, the SAFE Data Act specifies acceptable methods for notifying individuals and content requirements, and mandates the provision of free consumer credit reports and credit monitoring in certain instances.  Entities that comply with certain other federal laws with breach notification requirements would be deemed in compliance with the notification requirements of the SAFE Data Act.

Violations of the legislation would constitute unfair or deceptive acts or practices enforceable under the FTC Act and may result in civil penalties.  While state attorneys general also may bring civil actions on behalf of their residents, there is no private right of action.  With respect to state privacy laws, the SAFE Data Act would supersede any provision of a state statute, regulation or rule that expressly requires similar information security practices and breach notification to individuals.

###  [India Drafts New Privacy Regulations](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/05/articles/international/india-drafts-new-privacy-regulations/)

Posted on May 18, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On April 11, 2011, India [adopted new privacy regulations](http://www.mit.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/RNUS_CyberLaw_15411.pdf), known as the Information Technology (Reasonable Security Practices and Procedures and Sensitive Personal Data or Information) Rules, 2011 (the “Rules”).  The Rules are final versions of the [draft regulations issued in February 2011](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/02/articles/international/india-issues-draft-privacy-rules/) and impose wide-ranging obligations on any “body corporate” (company) that “collects, receives, possesses, stores, deals or handles” personal information.  These obligations require companies to provide privacy policies, restrict the processing of sensitive personal data, restrict international data transfers and require additional security measures.  The Rules introduce an omnibus privacy law that is similar in many respects to existing EU data protection law, but which raises some fundamental challenges for India’s numerous outsourcing vendors, and their customers.

**Key Provisions**

The Rules impose a number of additional obligations on organizations, as summarized below.

  * _Privacy Policy_ – The body corporate, or any person on its behalf, that “collects, receives, possesses, stores, deals or handles” personal information must provide a privacy policy that clearly sets out its practices and policies, identifies any sensitive personal data collected and processed, explains the purposes for which the data is collected and used, discloses specific information in relation to the newly defined category of “sensitive personal data,” and provides for reasonable security practices and procedures.
  * _Definition of Sensitive Personal Data_ – Sensitive personal data is now a defined term, although the definition is narrower than had originally been proposed in draft regulations.  Mirroring EU data protection law to some extent, sensitive personal data includes physical, physiological and mental health conditions, medical records and history, and sexual orientation.  The definition also includes biometric data, passwords and financial information such as bank account details, credit and debit card details.  Information that is freely available or accessible in the public domain or furnished under the Right to Information Act 2005 is excluded from the definition of sensitive personal data.
  * _Restrictions on Data Collection and Processing_ – At the point of collection of any data, individuals must be made aware of the fact that their data are being collected, the purpose for which the data are collected, the intended recipients of the data and the contact details of both the agency collecting the data and the agency that will retain the data.  Further, all data is subject to a restriction on any processing for secondary purposes.  It must be processed only for the purpose for which it was collected.
  * _Additional Restrictions for Sensitive Personal Data_ – The prior written consent of an individual is required before their sensitive personal data may be processed.  Consent may be obtained by letter, fax or email.  The provider of the sensitive personal data must be given the option, at the outset, not to provide data and may withdraw their consent to the processing at any time.  In addition, sensitive personal data may only be collected for a lawful purpose connected with a function or activity of the body corporate, and the collection of the data must be necessary for that purpose.  Sensitive personal data may not be retained for longer than required for the purpose for which it may lawfully be used.
  * _Rights of Access and Correction_ – Individuals have the right to review the information about them and to ensure that inaccurate or deficient data is corrected or amended, as feasible.
  * _Disclosure to Third Parties_ – Information (including sensitive personal data) may only be provided to a third party with the consent of the provider of the information.  There are exceptions where the disclosure has been agreed to contractually, is required for legal compliance purposes, or where the disclosure is to government agencies mandated to obtain the information for specific purposes.  The body corporate processing the information (or any person on its behalf) may not publish it and any third party recipient is prohibited from further disclosing the information.
  * _International Data Transfers_ – A body corporate or another person on its behalf may transfer sensitive personal data or information to another body corporate or person in India or abroad where the same level of data protection is assured.  The Rules also stipulate that “the transfer may be allowed only if it is necessary” for the performance of a lawful contract with the provider of the data or with their consent.
  * _Security_ – The Rules state that a body corporate will be taken to have complied with reasonable security practices and procedures where they have implemented those practices and have a comprehensive documented information security program and policies that contain managerial, technical, operational and physical control measures commensurate with the information assets and nature of the business.  In the event of a security breach, the organization must be able to demonstrate that it has implemented its documented security control measures when asked to do so.  An organization that has implemented International Standard IS/ISO/IEC 27001 or an approved industry code of practice is deemed to have complied with reasonable security practices and procedures, provided that compliance with the standard or code of practice has been audited annually.

It is not yet clear how the Rules will apply in practice, particularly in the context of data processing activities outsourced to India.  There is some ambiguity as to the extent to which the Rules will apply to local outsourcing vendors and/or to off-shore arrangements where data processing remains within the corporate group, albeit in India.  Existing contract terms also will be relevant to any assessment of whether existing data processing arrangements require amendment in light of the Rules.  Organizations with operations in India, or which use vendors based in India, will need to review their existing data processing arrangements in light of these new requirements.

[View the Rules](http://www.mit.gov.in/sites/upload_files/dit/files/RNUS_CyberLaw_15411.pdf).

###  [Court Finds Allegations of Harm Sufficient to Allow Breach-Related Class Action Suit to Proceed](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/04/articles/online-privacy/court-finds-allegations-of-harm-sufficient-to-allow-breachrelated-class-action-suit-to-proceed/)

Posted on April 22, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On April 11, 2011, the United States District Court for the Northern District of California [declined to dismiss](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/uploads/file/PrivacyLaw_Claridge_RockYou_Decision.pdf) four of the nine claims in a class action lawsuit filed against RockYou, Inc. (“RockYou”), a publisher and developer of applications used on popular social media sites.  The suit stems from a December 2009 security breach caused by an SQL injection flaw that resulted in the exposure of unencrypted user names and passwords of approximately 32 million RockYou users.  RockYou subsequently fixed the error and acknowledged in a public statement that “one or more individuals had illegally breached its databases” and that “at the time of the breach, the hacked database had not been up to date with industry standard security protocols.”  After receiving notification of the security breach from RockYou in mid-December, on December 28, 2009, a RockYou user who had signed up for a photo-sharing application filed a complaint seeking injunctive relief and damages for himself and on behalf of all other similarly-situated individuals.    

The plaintiff’s [complaint](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/uploads/file/PrivacyLaw_Claridge_Amended_complaint.pdf) (as amended on August 12, 2010) alleged that RockYou failed “to secure and safeguard users’ sensitive personally identifiable information (‘PII’), including e-mail addresses and passwords and login credentials for social networks” in violation of RockYou’s terms of service and “accepted, long-standing industry standards.”  Although RockYou’s privacy policy stated that “RockYou! uses commercially reasonable physical, managerial, and technical safeguards to preserve the integrity and security of your personal information,” the company failed to use any form of encryption to protect the PII, which was stored in “clear” or “plain text” format, and did not use “hashing, salting, or any other common and reasonable method of data protection and therefore drastically exacerbated the consequences of a hacker bypassing its outer layer of web security.”  

The plaintiff asserted nine causes of action against RockYou, five of which were dismissed in the April 11, 2011 order.  The remaining four claims (breach of contract, breach of implied contract, negligence and negligence per se) were not dismissed, leaving open the possibility that RockYou could be held liable for breach of contract with respect to data security promises it made in its online privacy policy.  The following are some key points from the court’s order.

  * The court ruled that the plaintiff’s allegations of harm were sufficient at that stage of the proceedings “to allege a generalized injury in fact” despite RockYou’s argument that the plaintiff had failed to sufficiently allege “any actionable harm or concrete, tangible, non-speculative harm or loss.” 
  * The court held that “[n]ot only is there a paucity of controlling authority regarding the legal sufficiency of plaintiff’s damages theory, but the court also takes note that the context in which plaintiff's theory arises — i.e., the unauthorized disclosure of personal information via the Internet — is itself relatively new, and therefore more likely to raise issues of law not yet settled in the courts.”  The court noted, however, that it has “doubts about plaintiff’s ultimate ability to prove his damages theory in this case.”  
  * RockYou challenged the plaintiff’s three contract-based claims (breach of contract, breach of implied contract, and breach of the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing) for failure to allege any actionable damages, and argued that the “contractual claims should be dismissed because the provisions of the privacy policy maintained by defendant expressly provide that no liability will result due to a third party’s unauthorized access of defendant’s computer system.”  According to the court, however, the relevant section of RockYou’s privacy policy indicated that RockYou “assumes no liability or responsibility for . . . any unauthorized access to or use of our secure servers and/or any and all personal information and/or financial information stored therein” and thus, “since plaintiff is alleging that the servers were not, in fact, secure, this provision of the policy does not automatically preclude plaintiff’s contract claims.”
  * The court refused to dismiss the plaintiff’s claims for breach of contract and breach of implied contract, but dismissed the claim for breach of the implied covenant of good faith and fair dealing because the plaintiff did not provide any “supporting or factual allegations that adequately allege the type of conscious and deliberate acts” required to prevail on this count. 
  * The court’s order allows the plaintiff to amend two of its claims, including the breach of implied contract claim, to re-allege any additional facts sufficient to state a proper claim.  The plaintiff has until May 11, 2011 to amend its complaint.  As the court noted, however, “[i]f it becomes apparent, through discovery, that no basis exists upon which plaintiff could legally demonstrate tangible harm via the unauthorized disclosure of personal information, the court will dismiss plaintiff’s claims for lack of standing at the dispositive motion stage.”

###  [Representative Stearns Introduces Consumer Privacy Protection Act](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/04/articles/online-privacy/representative-stearns-introduces-consumer-privacy-protection-act/)

Posted on April 15, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On April 13, 2011, Representative [Cliff Stearns](http://stearns.house.gov/News/DocumentSingle.aspx?DocumentID=236296) (R-FL) introduced the [Consumer Privacy Protection Act of 2011](http://stearns.house.gov/UploadedFiles/Privacy_Bill.pdf) (the “Act”), which seeks to “protect and enhance consumer privacy” both online and offline by imposing certain notice and choice requirements with respect to the collection and use of personal information.

The legislation would apply to any “covered entity,” which is defined as an entity “that collects…sells, discloses for consideration, or uses personally identifiable information of more than 5,000 consumers during any consecutive 12-month period” (excluding governmental agencies, providers of professional services obligated by rules of ethics and confidentiality requirements and data processing outsourcing entities).  The term “personally identifiable information” (“PII”) means “individually identifiable information relating to a living individual who can be identified from that information” and includes primary data elements ( _e.g._ , name, address, Social Security number), as well as birth date and an electronic address (including an IP address) when used in combination with one of the primary data elements.  The bill explicitly excludes from the definition of PII anonymous or aggregate data (or any other information that does not identify a unique living individual), information about a consumer inferred from data maintained about a consumer, and information about a consumer that is publicly available or obtained from a public record.

Among other requirements, the Act would obligate covered entities to:

  * Provide the consumer with a privacy notice before PII is used for a purpose unrelated to a “transaction” (which is broadly defined under the act to include interactions between the consumer and a covered entity resulting in (1) any use of the information that is necessary to complete the interaction in the course of which information is collected, or to maintain the provisions of a requested good or service; (2) any disclosure of information necessary for the consumer to enforce his or her right; (3) any disclosure required by law or court order; (4) any use to verify PII; and (5) the collection or use of PII for marketing or advertising the covered entity’s products or services to its customers or potential customers);
  * Provide the consumer with a privacy notice upon a material change in the covered entity’s privacy policy;
  * Provide the consumer with a clear and concise “privacy policy statement” (at the time the covered entity collects a consumer’s PII that may be used for a purpose unrelated to a transaction with the consumer) that discloses (1) the identity of each covered entity or each class or type of covered entity that may collect the information, (2) the type of information that may be collected or stored, (3) how the information may be used, (4) whether the consumer is required to provide the information to do business with the entity, (5) the extent to which the information is subject to sale or disclosure for consideration, and (6) whether the entity’s information security practices meet the requirements of the Act to prevent the unauthorized disclosure or release of PII;
  * Provide the consumer with the opportunity (at no charge) to prevent for up to five years the sale or disclosure for consideration of the consumer’s PII that may be used for a purpose other than a transaction with the consumer; and
  * Implement an information security policy that safeguards PII and is designed to prevent the unauthorized disclosure of release of such information.

Violations of the Act would constitute unfair or deceptive acts or practices and could result in civil penalties up to $500,000 for all related violations by a single violator.  The Act also instructs the FTC to approve self-regulatory programs for a period of five years that exempt participants from civil penalties imposed under the Act.  Finally, the Act provides that compliance with certain other federal privacy laws shall be deemed compliance with the Act and that the Act preempts state statutory laws and regulations to the extent they affect the collection or use of PII in commerce.

The Consumer Privacy Protection Act of 2011 joins a list of bills previously introduced in the past couple of months, including the [Commercial Privacy Bill of Rights Act of 2011](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/04/articles/centre-for-information-policy-2/senators-kerry-and-mccain-introduce-the-commercial-privacy-bill-of-rights-act-of-2011/), the [Do Not Track Me Online Act of 2011 and the Financial Information Privacy Act of 2011](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/02/articles/online-privacy/speier-introduces-privacy-legislation-package/).

Read the [full text of the bill](http://stearns.house.gov/UploadedFiles/Privacy_Bill.pdf).

###  [South Korea Enacts Comprehensive Privacy Law](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/04/articles/international/south-korea-enacts-comprehensive-privacy-law/)

Posted on April 1, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

As reported in _[BNA’s Privacy Law Watch](http://news.bna.com/pwdm/PWDMWB/split_display.adp?fedfid=20216163&vname=prabulallissues&fn=20216163&jd=a0c7f3h5a8&split=0)_ , on March 29, 2011, South Korea’s president approved the Act on the Protection of Personal Data.  This comprehensive privacy law will require nearly all businesses and government agencies to provide data breach protection, mandate the use of privacy assessments before establishing certain new databases, and establish a right to file class actions in court over alleged violations of the law.  The implementing rules will be worked out before the law is due to take effect on September 30, 2011.  South Korea first attempted to enact a comprehensive privacy law in 2004; however, for the past seven years, omnibus privacy bills sponsored by the government and lawmakers have stalled in Parliament.

According to the South Korean [Ministry of Public Administration and Security](http://www.mopas.go.kr/gpms/ns/mogaha/user/nolayout/main/english/userEngMainDisplay.action) (the “Ministry”), the data protection requirements of the new law will cover about 3.5 million public and private sector businesses and organizations, with 3 million being covered for the first time.  The comprehensive new law remedies “blind spots” and eliminates redundancies created by the previous patchwork of privacy regulations, and sets standard operating procedures at each stage of handling personal data.  The omnibus privacy law adheres to the established data protection principles regarding requiring prior consent for the collection, use, sharing and disposal of personal data.

According to the Ministry, the legislation will be effective particularly in preventing damage caused by leaked and misused personal data.  Under the new law, covered entities must report incidents of leaked personal data to government privacy and law enforcement authorities and notify affected individuals.  The new law also will require privacy assessments for large database development by public services providers.  In addition, individuals will have improved legal recourse for privacy infringement, such as (1) privacy telephone hotline centers to register data protection complaints; (2) a dispute mediation committee which can seek out-of-court privacy settlements; and (3) the option of filing a class action lawsuit.

The omnibus law will establish a centralized data protection planning and enforcement system in the form of a new presidential committee.  The Ministry has the ultimate responsibility for administering the new law and issuing three-year action plans to execute privacy policy programs.

###  [Google Settles FTC Deceptive Privacy Practice Charges Regarding Google Buzz](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/03/articles/enforcement-1/google-settles-ftc-deceptive-privacy-practice-charges-regarding-google-buzz/)

Posted on March 30, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On March 30, 2011, the Federal Trade Commission [announced](http://ftc.gov/opa/2011/03/google.shtm) that Google agreed to settle charges that it used deceptive tactics and violated its own privacy promises to consumers when it launched its social network, Google Buzz, in 2010.  According to the FTC’s complaint ([main document](http://ftc.gov/os/caselist/1023136/110330googlebuzzcmpt.pdf), [exhibits](http://ftc.gov/os/caselist/1023136/110330googlebuzzexhibit.pdf)), Google led Gmail users to believe that they could choose whether or not they wanted to join Google Buzz.  The options for declining or leaving Google Buzz, however, were ineffective.  For those who joined Google Buzz, the controls for limiting the sharing of their personal information were difficult to locate and confusing.  Furthermore, the FTC charged that Google violated its privacy policies by using information provided for Gmail for another purpose – social networking – without obtaining consumers’ permission in advance.  Finally, the FTC alleged that Google misrepresented that it was treating personal information from the European Union in accordance with the U.S.-EU Safe Harbor framework because it failed to give consumers notice and choice before using their information for a different purpose from that for which it was collected.

The [proposed settlement](http://ftc.gov/os/caselist/1023136/110330googlebuzzagreeorder.pdf) requires Google to obtain consumers’ consent before sharing their information with third parties if Google modifies its sharing practices as a result of changes to Google’s products or services.  Google also must establish and maintain a comprehensive privacy program that is reasonably designed to: (1) address privacy risks related to the development and management of new and existing products and services for consumers, and (2) protect the privacy and confidentiality of covered information.  Google is required to obtain initial and biennial assessments for 20 years from an independent auditor to ensure that it is following the required comprehensive privacy program.

The proposed settlement with Google marks the first time that the FTC will require a company to implement a comprehensive privacy program (as opposed to a comprehensive security program), with biennial audits for 20 years, and it contains the FTC’s first substantive privacy allegations regarding failure to comply with the U.S.-EU Safe Harbor Program.  Previous [Safe Harbor-related enforcement actions](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2009/10/articles/enforcement-1/ftc-takes-additional-safe-harborrelated-enforcement-actions/) focused on organizations that falsely claimed membership in the program even after their certifications had lapsed.  

###  [Department of Commerce Official Asks Congress to Enact "Privacy Bill of Rights"](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/03/articles/enforcement-1/department-of-commerce-official-asks-congress-to-enact-privacy-bill-of-rights/)

Posted on March 16, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On March 16, 2011, U.S. Department of Commerce Assistant Secretary for Communications and Information Lawrence Strickling called on Congress to enact robust, baseline legislation to “reform consumer data privacy in the Internet economy.” Speaking before the U.S. Senate Committee on Commerce, Science and Transportation, Assistant Secretary Strickling emphasized the Department of Commerce’s support for a legislative proposal that would adopt many of the recommendations of the “[Green Paper](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/12/articles/information-security/department-of-commerce-issues-landmark-privacy-green-paper/),” a Department report authored last December.

In [prepared remarks](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/uploads/file/Strickling_Testimony.PDF), Assistant Secretary Strickling stated, “Having carefully reviewed all stakeholder comments to the Green Paper, the Department has concluded that the U.S. consumer data privacy framework will benefit from legislation to establish a clearer set of rules for the road for businesses and consumers, while preserving the innovation and free flow of information that are hallmarks of the Internet.”

The proposed legislation would include several key elements, such as:

  * Enacting a baseline “Consumer Privacy Bill of Rights” that invokes several Fair Information Practice Principles discussed in the Green Paper;
  * Implementing online Codes of Conduct developed through the input of diverse stakeholders, including individuals from government agencies and the commercial, consumer advocacy and academic sectors;
  * Empowering the Federal Trade Commission to enforce the legislation's provisions while creating industry incentives for compliance; and
  * Establishing limiting principles to avoid duplicative and cumbersome privacy legislation while achieving a clear statutory regime.

Among its next steps in crafting its Internet privacy policy, Assistant Secretary Strickling noted the Department of Commerce’s potential role in mediating discussions and highlighted the Obama administration’s involvement with the National Strategy for Trusted Identities in Cyberspace, a separate initiative that “envisions enhancing online privacy and security through services that provide credentials that improve upon the username and password schemes that are common online.” 

View a copy of Assistant Secretary Strickling’s [prepared testimony](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/uploads/file/Strickling_Testimony.PDF).

###  [FTC Accepts Final Settlement with Twitter](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/03/articles/enforcement-1/ftc-accepts-final-settlement-with-twitter/)

Posted on March 14, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On March 11, 2011, the Federal Trade Commission [finalized](http://www.ftc.gov/opa/2011/03/twitter.shtm) a proposed settlement with Twitter, which resolved allegations that Twitter deceived consumers and failed to safeguard their personal information. The FTC first announced the [proposed settlement](http://www.ftc.gov/os/caselist/0923093/110311twitterdo.pdf) in June 2010. Specifically, the FTC [claimed](http://www.ftc.gov/os/caselist/0923093/110311twittercmpt.pdf) that Twitter, contrary to its privacy policy statements, did not provide reasonable and appropriate security to prevent unauthorized access to consumers’ personal information and did not honor the consumers’ privacy choices in designating certain tweets as nonpublic. Intruders exploited these failures and obtained administrative control of the Twitter system. These intruders were able to gain unauthorized access to nonpublic tweets and user information, reset any user’s password, and send unauthorized tweets from any user account.

Under the terms of the settlement, Twitter must implement a comprehensive information security program that is reasonably designed to protect the privacy and security of nonpublic consumer information, and it is prohibited from misrepresenting the extent to which it protects such information. An independent auditor must conduct biennial assessments for 10 years to determine whether Twitter’s information security program adequately protects consumer information as required by the settlement. Twitter is further required to make available to the FTC any privacy policy statements, consumer complaints, subpoenas and other documents that relate to Twitter’s activities in the FTC complaint or Twitter’s compliance in the settlement. Finally, Twitter must file a report describing its compliance with the settlement and alert the FTC to any change in the corporation that may affect its compliance obligations. Any violation of the FTC order, which is in effect for 20 years, may result in a civil penalty of up to $16,000. The order is in effect for 20 years.

###  [German Federal DPA Approves Binding Corporate Rules of Deutsche Post DHL](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2011/02/articles/european-union-1/german-federal-dpa-approves-binding-corporate-rules-of-deutsche-post-dhl/)

Posted on February 3, 2011 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On February 3, 2011, the German Federal Commissioner for Data Protection and Freedom of Information issued a [press release](http://www.bfdi.bund.de/cln_136/DE/Oeffentlichkeitsarbeit/Pressemitteilungen/2011/5_BCRUebergabeAnDPAG.html?nn=408920) announcing that it has approved the privacy policy formulated by Deutsche Post DHL.  This allows Deutsche Post DHL to transfer personal data abroad in accordance with its privacy policy without having to obtain approval in individual cases.  Deutsche Post DHL is the first German company to have its binding corporate rules (“BCRs”) approved at the European level, following an extensive consultation process among EU data protection authorities.

Deutsche Post DHL is a global company with approximately 500,000 employees in 220 countries and territories whose business operations include frequent cross-border exchanges of customer and employee data.  The transfer of personal data outside the European Union and outside the EEA, however, requires proof of an adequate level of protection under the German Federal Data Protection Act.  Pursuant to Section 4 (2) of the Act, the competent data protection authority may approve international data transfers based on an entity’s BCRs.  Accordingly, Deutsche Post DHL included in its privacy policy the necessary guarantees concerning the protection of personal data and the corresponding rights of individuals, and demonstrated the enforceability of its rules.

For further information, please contact [Dr. Jörg Hladjk](http://www.hunton.com/bios/bio.aspx?id=16849&tab=0013) in the Brussels office of Hunton & Williams.  

###  [Vladeck Previews Long-Awaited FTC Report](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/12/articles/enforcement-1/vladeck-previews-longawaited-ftc-report/)

Posted on December 1, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

David Vladeck, Director of the FTC’s Division of Consumer Protection, this morning previewed the long-awaited FTC report that sums up months of discussion regarding the future of privacy regulation in the United States and examines the viability of a Do Not Track mechanism.  Vladeck indicated at the Consumer Watchdog Policy Conference that the existing privacy framework in the U.S. is not keeping pace with new technologies.  In addition, he stated that the pace of industry self-regulation, while constructive, has been too slow.  According to Vladeck, the report will address several major themes, including the following:

  * There is a need to reduce the burden on consumers to allow them to control their information more effectively.  Vladeck provided several examples of ways to reduce this burden: 
    * Privacy by Design, which entails building privacy protections into products and services at the outset and practicing good data hygiene from the start.  Vladeck noted that the more companies do on the front end, the less burden there will be on consumers on the back end. 
    * Greatly simplify consumer choice, which involves streamlining choice mechanisms so consumers can focus on choices that really matter to them, such as uses of data they would not expect.  Choice should be presented in a short and concise manner at the point of collection. 
    * More consistent privacy policies that would allow consumers to compare companies’ privacy practices at a glance. 
  * Strong protections are needed for sensitive information, which includes health, financial, children’s and geolocation data.
  * Once consumers exercise choice, it must be respected.  Vladeck indicated that the FTC would not tolerate a “technological arms race aimed at subverting” consumer choice.
  * Privacy policies are here to stay.  But to help promote accountability, we need better privacy policies and must reduce the current dependency on the notice and choice framework. 
  * Data brokers will continue to be in the spotlight.  The FTC views access to data maintained by data brokers as “a key ingredient” of accountability.
  * Consumer and business education is a critical issue.  There is a need to broaden and deepen consumers’ understanding of organizations’ information practices so consumers can take steps necessary to protect their privacy.

Recognizing that consumers want control over their data, the FTC report explores a Do Not Track mechanism where marketers would need  to respect consumer choice.  While acknowledging that there have been some industry efforts along these lines, Vladeck believes the options are too disparate.  He stressed the need to simplify consumer choice.  The FTC believes that a Do Not Track mechanism would help to achieve this goal.

Vladeck indicated that the report will mark the end of Phase One of the FTC’s “privacy rethink” project, and lays out a basic framework for moving forward.  The FTC is seeking comments, which are due January 31, 2011. 

  We will provide continuing coverage throughout the day regarding the FTC’s report, which is scheduled to be issued at 11 a.m. EST.

###  [Department of Commerce Provides Insight on Upcoming Privacy Paper](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/11/articles/centre-for-information-policy-2/department-of-commerce-provides-insight-on-upcoming-privacy-paper/)

Posted on November 15, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

Earlier today, a Department of Commerce official briefed Hunton & Williams and Centre for Information Policy Leadership representatives on the Department’s forthcoming “Green Paper” on privacy.  On November 12, 2010, _[Telecommunications Reports Daily](http://www.tr.com/newsletters/trd/)_ published an article based on information obtained from an unofficial, pre-release draft version of the Green Paper.  It remains to be seen which portions of the leaked draft ultimately will survive the interagency approval process currently underway.  The Department of Commerce representative emphasized that the content of the draft Green Paper currently undergoing review is consistent with Assistant Secretary of Commerce [Larry Strickling’s October 27, 2010, speech in Jerusalem](http://www.ntia.doc.gov/presentations/2010/IntlConfDataProtectionPrivacyCommissioners_10272010.html).  In his speech, Secretary Strickling explained that the Department is calling it a “Green” Paper, “not because of its environmental impact, but because it contains both recommendations and a further set of questions on topics about which [the Department] seek[s] further input.”

The Commerce Department representative confirmed that quotes contained in the _TR Daily_ article are indeed found in the current version of the Green Paper, but characterized as inaccurate certain implications found in other media accounts regarding the report.  For example, although a [_New York Times_ article](http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/10/business/media/10privacy.html?) suggested a possible conflict between a paper being prepared by the Federal Trade Commission and the Department of Commerce’s Green Paper, the Commerce Department representative indicated that this is not the case – the two entities have shared drafts of their respective reports and Commerce considers them to be “perfectly aligned.”  Commerce believes that the FTC should continue to function as the lead enforcement agency for privacy issues, but also sees a role for a new privacy policy agency that would function in cooperation with the FTC.  This new privacy body might be located in the White House or the Commerce Department, and would liaise with businesses seeking to develop new solutions to emerging privacy issues.  The current version of the Green Paper also highlights the Department of Commerce’s support for new federal legislation based on Fair Information Practice Principles, in conjunction with industry self-regulation.

The Department of Commerce representative indicated that [input provided by the Centre for Information Policy Leadership](http://www.huntonfiles.com/files/webupload/PrivacyLaw_Centre_Comments_to_DOC.pdf) has been influential in the development of the Green Paper.  According to the Centre’s Executive Director, Marty Abrams, these contributions are reflective of ongoing work the Centre has been undertaking to link technological innovation and accountability.  In June of this year, we [reported on the Centre’s involvement](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/06/articles/enforcement-1/centre-offers-ten-recommendations-in-response-to-commerce-department-inquiry/) with the Commerce Department’s [initial inquiry](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/04/articles/international/department-of-commerce-to-seek-public-comment-on-privacy-issues/).

It is not clear at this time when the Green Paper will be issued, but it is expected before the end of this year.  The document will contain numerous questions and a solicitation for comments from interested stakeholders. We will provide additional coverage as this story develops.

###  [Live Coverage from Jerusalem: Vladeck Provides Overview of Upcoming FTC Report](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/10/articles/events/live-coverage-from-jerusalem-vladeck-provides-overview-of-upcoming-ftc-report/)

Posted on October 28, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

David Vladeck, Director of the Bureau of Consumer Protection of the Federal Trade Commission, today provided a high-level outline of the Commission’s forthcoming report on the future of privacy.

Speaking at the [32nd International Conference of Data Protection and Privacy Commissioners](http://www.privacyconference2010.org/) in Jerusalem, Vladeck said the report reflected two broad conclusions.  First, current privacy law places too much burden on consumers to read and understand privacy notices and make privacy choices.  The second conclusion is that there is a pressing need to reexamine the conception of “harm” in U.S. law to move beyond only economic and physical harms.

According to Vladeck, the Commission’s report offers three tentative recommendations based on these conclusions.  Businesses need to:

  1. Do more on the front end to preserve privacy.
  2. Better align their data practices with consumers’ reasonable expectations, for example, by avoiding practices that consumers don’t anticipate or that are inimical to their interests.
  3. Be more transparent in their data collection and use practices, for example, by providing short, concise, just-in-time notices that clearly indicate who is collecting data, what data are being collected, and for what purposes.

Vladeck concluded by noting that the draft report contains a “last plank on consumer education,” highlighting the need for both business and government to educate consumers about privacy protections and risks.

The FTC report, which follows the Commission’s three workshops on privacy, is expected out by Thanksgiving.

###  [Bankrupt Magazine Must Destroy Readers' Personal Information](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/08/articles/enforcement-1/bankrupt-magazine-must-destroy-readers-personal-information/)

Posted on August 17, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

As we [recently reported](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/07/articles/online-privacy/ftcs-david-vladeck-opposes-bankruptcy-transfer-of-personal-information/), the FTC expressed its opposition to a move by creditors of bankrupt _XY Magazine_ to acquire personal information about the magazine’s subscribers, on the grounds that such a transfer would contravene the magazine’s privacy promises and could violate the Federal Trade Commission Act.  The magazine, which catered to a young gay audience, had a website privacy policy that asserted   “[w]e never give your info to anybody” and “our privacy policy is simple: we never share your information with anybody.”  Readers who submitted online profile information were told that their information “will not be published.  We keep it secret.”  The personal information at issue included the names, postal and email addresses, photographs and online profiles of more than 500,000 users.

As reported in _[BNA’s Privacy Law Watch](http://news.bna.com/pwdm/PWDMWB/split_display.adp?fedfid=17638109&vname=prabulallissues&fn=17638109&jd=17638109)_ , as a result of the FTC’s opposition to the transfer of the personal information, the parties entered into a consent order agreeing that the information will be destroyed before the magazine’s assets are sold.  The [consent order](http://op.bna.com/pl.nsf/r?Open=dapn-88dl3c) called for the destruction to be carried out in a manner that will make the information “unreadable, undecipherable, or non-reconstructable through generally available means.”

This incident is a reminder of the legal significance of privacy promises made outside the context of an actual privacy policy.  It also highlights the need to anticipate changes in business circumstances (such as mergers or sales of assets) when making any privacy representations. Inappropriate commitments may prove damaging to the company, its investors and creditors.  Read more about [emerging privacy issues in bankruptcy](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/06/articles/enforcement-1/emerging-privacy-issues-in-bankruptcy/) in an [article published by _GC New York_](http://www.hunton.com/files/tbl_s47Details/FileUpload265/2893/Emerging_Privacy_Issues_in_Bankruptcy_6.10.10.pdf).

###  [FTC's David Vladeck Opposes Bankruptcy Transfer of Personal Information](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/07/articles/online-privacy/ftcs-david-vladeck-opposes-bankruptcy-transfer-of-personal-information/)

Posted on July 15, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

David Vladeck, Director of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection, recently sent a [letter](http://www.ftc.gov/os/closings/100712xy.pdf) to creditors of _XY Magazine_ , warning that the creditors’ acquisition of personal information about the debtor’s subscribers and readers in contravention of the debtor’s privacy promises could violate the Federal Trade Commission Act (“FTC Act”).

Vladeck’s letter explained that, since its inception, the debtor’s website “Sign-up Confirmation Page” told potential members/subscribers: “Please note our amazing privacy policy. We never give your info to anybody.”  Another representation, which appeared on the website and was directed to magazine subscribers, stated: “[O]ur privacy policy is simple: we never share your information with anybody.”  Those submitting online profile information were told that such information “will not be published. [W]e keep it secret.”  The magazine catered to a young gay audience, including individuals whose sexual orientation was a secret.  The creditors have been seeking to acquire the magazine’s subscriber information, among other assets.  Under these circumstances, Vladeck argues, a transfer of the information to the creditors would contradict the privacy statements made to the subscribers, in possible violation of the FTC Act’s prohibition against “unfair or deceptive acts or practices.”

This incident is a reminder of the legal significance of privacy promises made outside the context of an actual privacy policy, and it highlights the need to anticipate changes in business circumstances (such as mergers or sales of assets) when making any privacy representations.  Inappropriate commitments may prove damaging to the company, its investors and creditors.  Read more about [emerging privacy issues in bankruptcy](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/06/articles/enforcement-1/emerging-privacy-issues-in-bankruptcy/) in an [article published by GC New York](http://www.hunton.com/files/tbl_s47Details/FileUpload265/2893/Emerging_Privacy_Issues_in_Bankruptcy_6.10.10.pdf) by [Lisa J. Sotto](http://www.hunton.com/bios/bio.aspx?id=14751&BioID=943&BioType=Group), [Scott H. Bernstein](http://www.hunton.com/bios/bio.aspx?id=17546&tab=0013) and Boris Segalis.

###  [Commerce Department Takes Lead in Developing U.S. Internet Privacy Framework](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/05/articles/centre-for-information-policy-2/commerce-department-takes-lead-in-developing-us-internet-privacy-framework/)

Posted on May 11, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

“The Department of Commerce is back.”  With those words Cameron Kerry, General Counsel of the U.S. Department of Commerce, made it clear the Department intends to take a leading role in shaping domestic privacy policy and representing U.S. privacy interests in international discussions.  The announcement was made at the May 7, 2010, Department of Commerce symposium, “[A Dialogue on Privacy and Innovation](http://www.ntia.doc.gov/internetpolicytaskforce/privacy/symposiumagenda_05072010.pdf),” where the mostly business audience welcomed Mr. Kerry’s declaration with great enthusiasm.

In the 1990’s, during the Clinton Administration, the Department of Commerce led U.S. efforts to develop policy related to privacy on the Internet and encouraged the development of online privacy policies and privacy seal programs.  Within the Department, the National Telecommunications and Information Administration (“NTIA”) authored numerous privacy position papers, and the International Trade Commission (“ITA”) negotiated the U.S.-European Union Safe Harbor Framework.  During the Bush Administration and the first year of Obama’s tenure, however, the Department was largely silent on privacy issues. 

Beginning last fall, the Department began holding sessions to investigate the effectiveness of privacy protections in the United States and the impact of privacy regulation on businesses.  The sessions were led by Marc Berejka, Senior Policy Advisor in the Secretary’s Office at the Department of Commerce, and Danny Weitzner, Associate Administrator for the NTIA’s Office of Policy Analysis and Development.  Over the past few months, the Department, in conjunction with NTIA and ITA, formed the Internet Policy Task Force and issued a notice of inquiry to discuss the “[nexus between privacy policy and innovation in the Internet economy](http://www.ntia.doc.gov/frnotices/2010/FR_PrivacySymposium_04162010.pdf).” 

Last Friday’s day-long symposium included an introductory discussion on the global Internet economy and privacy that was followed by four panel discussions.  Professor [Fred Cate](http://www.hunton.com/bios/bio.aspx?id=15593&tab=0013), Senior Policy Advisor with the [Centre for Information Policy Leadership](http://www.hunton.com/Resources/Sites/general.aspx?id=45) and Distinguished Professor of Law at Indiana University Law School, set the stage for the first panel on “[Privacy, Innovation and Global Trade](http://www.huntonfiles.com/files/webupload/PrivacyLaw_Privacy_Innovation_and_Global_Trade_Panel.pdf).”  The participation of other Obama administration officials indicated that the Department is not alone in these efforts.  White House Deputy Chief Technology Officer Andrew McLaughlin led a panel on “Privacy Frameworks and Innovative Uses of Personal Information,” and Deputy Assistant Secretary of State and U.S. Coordinator for International Communications and Information Policy Phil Verveer spoke on the “Privacy on the Ground” panel. 

  The Department of Commerce will be receiving comments until June 7, 2010, on the [notice of inquiry it issued on April 20, 2010](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/04/articles/international/department-of-commerce-to-seek-public-comment-on-privacy-issues/).  A draft paper is expected in early October, ahead of the Organization of Economic and Cooperation and Development’s conference on privacy and technology, and the 32nd International Data Protection and Privacy Commissioners Conference, both of which will take place in Jerusalem during the last week of October.

###  [Department of Commerce Announces a Public Meeting on "Information Privacy and Innovation in the Internet Economy"](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/04/articles/centre-for-information-policy-2/department-of-commerce-announces-a-public-meeting-on-information-privacy-and-innovation-in-the-internet-economy/)

Posted on April 16, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

The Department of Commerce (“DOC”) will be holding a [public meeting](http://www.huntonfiles.com/files/webupload/PrivacyLaw_May_7_Federal_Register_Notice.pdf) on May 7, 2010, in Washington, D.C., to listen to stakeholders’ views on privacy policies in the United States.  This session is part of a broader inquiry by the DOC’s newly created Internet Policy Task Force “whose mission is to identify leading public policy and operational challenges in the Internet environment.”  The DOC’s National Telecommunications and Information Administration and the International Trade Administration will issue a notice of inquiry to look at the nexus between innovation and privacy on the Internet.  The Centre for Information Policy Leadership will be participating in these processes.

###  [Canadian Privacy Commissioner Investigates Facebook](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/02/articles/international/canadian-privacy-commissioner-investigates-facebook/)

Posted on February 4, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

Pursuant to a public complaint, on January 27, 2010, the Privacy Commissioner of Canada announced a new investigation into Facebook.  The investigation concerns the social networking site’s introduction of a tool that required its users to review their privacy settings in December 2009.  According to the complaint, Facebook’s new default settings allegedly made some users’ information more accessible than previously had been the case.  Elizabeth Denham, the Assistant Privacy Commissioner, indicated “[s]ome Facebook users are disappointed by certain changes being made to the site – changes that were supposed to strengthen their privacy and the protection of their personal information.”

The new complaint follows the Commissioner’s July 2009 release of findings resulting from an investigation into Facebook’s privacy policies and practices.  The findings highlighted concerns regarding Facebook, including a need for increased transparency and clarity.  The Office of the Privacy Commissioner will continue to follow up with Facebook as the company implements changes to its site.  

For further information, please see the Office of the Privacy Commissioner's [News Release](http://www.priv.gc.ca/media/nr-c/2010/nr-c_100127_e.cfm).

###  [Federal Trade Commission: Is Privacy Moving to a Post-Disclosure Era?](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2010/01/articles/enforcement-1/federal-trade-commission-is-privacy-moving-to-a-postdisclosure-era/)

Posted on January 12, 2010 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

In a discussion with _The New York Times_ , Federal Trade Commission (“FTC”) Chairman Jon Leibowitz, and chief of the FTC’s Bureau of Consumer Protection, David Vladeck, indicated that Internet publishers and advertisers can expect the FTC to play a more active role in safeguarding consumer privacy.  Chairman Leibowitz highlighted that, in the past, the FTC’s approach to privacy has focused on consumer notice and consent, and whether consumers were harmed.  From the FTC’s perspective, however, the present model is problematic because companies have failed to provide consumers with meaningful notice that would allow them to make effective choices regarding their privacy.  This “advise-and-consent” model is broken, as it “depended on the fiction that people were meaningfully giving consent.”  In reality, few consumers take the time to inform themselves about the notices and choices outlined in privacy policies.

The lack of meaningful consent has raised the possibility that privacy is moving beyond the advise-and-consent model toward a post-disclosure era.  It remains to be seen how the post-disclosure era will evolve and how the new paradigm will replace consumer notice and choice.  The FTC is examining the issue, and aims to publish a report by July 2010.  Although the final content of the report is yet to be determined, Chairman Leibowitz stated, “I have a sense, and it’s still amorphous, that we might head toward opt-in.”

For further information, view [_The New York Times_ blog post](http://mediadecoder.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/01/11/ftc-has-internet-gone-beyond-privacy-policies/).

###  [Privacy Group Files FTC Complaint Against Facebook](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2009/12/articles/online-privacy/privacy-group-files-ftc-complaint-against-facebook/)

Posted on December 18, 2009 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

On December 17, 2009, the Electronic Privacy Information Center (“EPIC”) filed a [complaint ](http://epic.org/privacy/inrefacebook/EPIC-FacebookComplaint.pdf)with the FTC claiming that Facebook is engaging “unfair and deceptive trade practices” by changing its privacy policies.  Notably, the changes allow anyone who browses the Internet to view a Facebook user’s name, profile picture, gender, geographic region and list of friends.  Facebook has stated that it implemented these changes to make it easier to find individual users among the estimated 350 million Facebook users.

EPIC’s complaint, which was signed by nine other privacy organizations, alleges that Facebook’s privacy changes injure users by “invading their privacy; allowing for disclosure and use of information in ways and for purposes other than those consented to or relied upon by such users; causing them to believe falsely that they have full control over the use of their information; and undermining the ability of users to avail themselves of the privacy protections promised by the company.”  EPIC’s complaint further alleges that Facebook’s claim that users “have extensive and precise controls available to choose who sees what among their network and friends, as well as tools that give them the choice to make a limited set of information available to search engines and other outside entities” is deceptive because “Facebook’s changes to users’ privacy settings and associated policies in fact categorize as ‘publicly available information’ users’ names, profile photos, lists of friends, pages they are fans of, gender, geographic regions, and networks to which they belong.”

EPIC is requesting the FTC compel Facebook to “restore its previous privacy settings” and “make its data collection practices clearer and more comprehensible and to give Facebook users meaningful control over personal information provided by Facebook to advertisers and developers.”  In response to EPIC’s complaint, Facebook released a statement that the company had “discussed the privacy program with many regulators, including the FTC, prior to launch and expect to continue to work with them in the future.”  

###  [Class Action Lawsuit Against Heartland Dismissed](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2009/12/articles/security-breach/class-action-lawsuit-against-heartland-dismissed/)

Posted on December 14, 2009 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

The court in [In re Heartland Payment Systems, Inc. Securities Litigation](http://www.huntonfiles.com/files/webupload/PrivacyLaw_Heartland_Decision.pdf), Civ. No. 09-1043 (D. N.J. Dec. 12, 2009) recently dismissed a class action lawsuit brought by investors in Heartland, a processor of payment card transactions whose stock value dropped significantly after it suffered a data security breach in which hackers allegedly stole 130 million payment card numbers.  The plaintiffs argued that Heartland’s statements to the effect that it had adequate security systems and that it took the issue of computer network security very seriously were fraudulent because Heartland knew it had poor data security and failed to remedy critical problems soon enough to prevent the theft.

According to the complaint, in December 2007, a group of hackers now under criminal indictment launched an attack on Heartland’s network, injecting malicious code into Heartland’s computers.  Heartland allegedly discovered this injection of malicious code and took remedial steps that failed to fully eradicate the threat.  Later, in 2008, the hackers used the injected code to steal millions of payment card numbers.  Heartland did not discover the theft until January 2009. 

The plaintiffs argued that Heartland had made various representations to investors that it maintained sufficient security to prevent such hacking.  For example, [Heartland’s 2007 Annual Report ](http://www.secinfo.com/d14D5a.t1Y5r.htm)discussed the company’s network security situation stating that Heartland “place[d] significant emphasis on maintaining a high level of security” and maintained a network configuration that “provides multiple layers of security to isolate our databases from unauthorized access.”

The court disagreed with the plaintiffs’ claim that these statements were untruthful, holding that “there is nothing inconsistent between Defendants’ statements and the fact that Heartland had suffered an … attack.”  The court explained that “[t]he fact that a company has suffered a security breach does not demonstrate that the company did not ‘place significant emphasis on maintaining a high level of security,’” because “[i]t is equally plausible that Heartland did place a high emphasis on security but that the Company’s security systems were nonetheless overcome.” 

With respect to a former Heartland IT employee’s statement that Heartland should have taken various additional steps to secure its network following the 2007 attack, the court found that “one former employee’s opinion that Heartland did not do everything it could have done to address the security breach does not render the statement ‘We place significant emphasis on maintaining a high level of security’ false.” 

In the end, the court dismissed the complaint against Heartland with prejudice, finding that, because the company “did not make any statements to the effect that the company’s network was immune from security breaches or that no security breach had ever occurred, …the statements in the 10-K were not false or misleading.”

###  [Washington Court Rules that IP Addresses Are Not Personally Identifiable Information](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2009/07/articles/online-privacy/washington-court-rules-that-ip-addresses-are-not-personally-identifiable-information/)

Posted on July 10, 2009 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

In a closely-watched case, the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Washington recently held that Internet Protocol (“IP”) addresses do not constitute personally identifiable information (“PII”). The plaintiffs in _Johnson v. Microsoft Corp._ brought a class action suit against Microsoft claiming that the collection of consumer IP addresses during the Windows XP installation process violated the XP End User License Agreement. The Agreement stated that Microsoft would not collect PII without the user’s consent. The plaintiffs referenced Microsoft’s own online glossary to support their claim that IP addresses should be considered PII. The glossary defined “personally identifiable information” as “[a]ny information relating to an identified or identifiable individual. Such information may include…IP address.” In granting summary judgment in favor of Microsoft, U.S. District Court Judge Richard Jones found that “[i]n order for ‘personally identifiable information’ to be personally identifiable, it must identify a person. But an IP address identifies a computer.”

The Washington court’s ruling diverges from other recent rulings in the United States and Europe. In 2008, New Jersey’s Supreme Court held that Internet Service Providers (“ISPs”) are forbidden from disclosing subscriber IP addresses without a subpoena. The court held that New Jersey citizens have a “reasonable expectation of privacy” in the “subscriber information they provide to Internet service providers – just as New Jersey citizens have a privacy interest in their bank records stored by banks and telephone billing records kept by phone companies.” _State v. Reid_ , 954 A.2d 503 (N.J. 2008).

Similarly, the European Union’s Article 29 Data Protection Working Party has noted that ISPs should “treat all IP information as personal data” unless the ISPs can “distinguish with absolute certainty that the data correspond to users that cannot be identified.” The Working Party has recommended that search engines delete or anonymize IP addresses once they are no longer needed, and should not retain the data longer than six months.

The issue of whether IP addresses are considered PII as a matter of law has significant implications for companies that collect and use consumer online information. To the extent IP addresses are considered PII, companies that use IP addresses for business purposes would be required to comply with numerous legal requirements with respect to that data.

###  [Alleged Violations of a Privacy Policy](http://www.huntonprivacyblog.com/2009/02/articles/financial-privacy/alleged-violations-of-a-privacy-policy/)

Posted on February 4, 2009 by [Hunton & Williams LLP](http://www.hunton.com/)

A recent federal court decision offers a detailed analysis of several theories of liability for violations of a privacy policy.  _Pinero v. Jackson Hewitt Tax Service Inc_., No. 08-3535, 2009 WL 43098 (E.D. La. January 7, 2009). 

Plaintiff Pinero visited Jackson Hewitt Tax Service in Louisiana to have her tax returns prepared.  During her visit, she provided Jackson Hewitt with confidential information such as her Social Security number, date of birth and driver’s license number.  Pinero signed Jackson Hewitt’s privacy policy, which stated that Jackson Hewitt had policies and procedures in place, including physical, electronic, and procedural safeguards, to protect customers' private information.  Pinero alleged that she relied on this statement in her decision to turn over her information.

Pinero contended that sometime in early 2008, defendants disposed of her 2005 federal and state tax returns intact in a public dumpster.  An unrelated individual found Pinero’s tax returns, as well as those of over 100 other people, and alerted a local television news station.

Pinero brought a putative class action, asserting state law claims of fraud, breach of contract, negligence, invasion of privacy, violation of the Louisiana Database Security Breach Notification Law ("LDSBNA") and violation of the Louisiana Unfair Trade Practices Act (LUTPA).  She also alleged that Jackson Hewitt violated 26 U.S.C. § 6103, which restricts certain disclosures of tax returns.  Pinero sought general damages for fear, panic, anxiety, sleeplessness, nightmares, embarrassment, hassle, anger, lost time, loss of consortium, and other emotional and physical distress, as well as special damages for credit monitoring, credit insurance, reimbursement for all out-of-pocket expenses related to notifying creditors of the improper disclosure, and reimbursement for all out-of-pocket expenses related to identity theft.

Jackson Hewitt moved to dismiss all claims.  Highlights of the court’s decision include:

  * Dismissal of the negligence claim because the increased risk of identity theft is too speculative to qualify as actual damage;
  * dismissal of the LDSBNA claim, in part because it only applies to breaches of computerized data;
  * dismissal of the contract claim, in part because expenses related to credit monitoring to guard against future identity theft are not compensable damages;
  * dismissal of the fraud and LUTPA claims (with leave to re-plead) for failure to explain why the representations in the privacy policy were misleading, since the mere breach of those promises does not alone establish that they were fraudulent;
  * dismissal of the claim under 26 U.S.C. § 6103, since that statute only prohibits disclosure of tax returns by persons to whom access to tax returns was granted by the IRS; and
  * denial of the motion to dismiss the invasion of privacy claim, since the alleged facts supported a claim for unreasonable public disclosure of private facts.

In response to this decision, Pinero filed an amended class-action complaint, re-pleading the fraud and LUPTA claims and maintaining the invasion of privacy claim.
